Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and we've got a very sad dialogue today actually, Marco.
我是Catherine，今天我们有一个非常悲伤的对话，Marco。
That's right.
没错。
Today we have a very sad but interesting dialogue of something that happens all the time.
今天我们有一个非常悲伤但有趣的对话，讲的是经常发生的事情。
Maybe you have a girlfriend, maybe you had a boyfriend and you break up.
也许你有女朋友，也许你有男朋友，然后你们分手了。
That means you are no longer boyfriend and girlfriend.
这意味着你们不再是男女朋友了。
Let's take a listen to today's dialogue and we'll be back in a moment to talk about what's
让我们听听今天的对话，稍后我们会回来讨论
going on.
发生了什么。
Hello.
你好。
Hey, do you want to go out tonight?
嘿，今晚想出去吗？
No, I think I'll pass.
不，我想我就不去了。
Mark broke up with me.
Mark和我分手了。
I feel awful.
我感觉糟透了。
What?
什么？
What happened?
发生什么事了？
Just last week you were talking about going on vacation together.
就在上周你还在说一起去度假的事。
I don't know what I did wrong.
我不知道我做错了什么。
He said he needed some space to figure things out.
他说他需要一些空间来理清事情。
He said I didn't do anything wrong, that I'm a great person, just not the one for him.
他说我没做错什么，我是个好人，只是不适合他。
That's so cliche.
这太老套了。
Mark's not worth your time, Lydia.
Mark不值得你浪费时间，Lydia。
You deserve so much better.
你值得更好的。
I know we had hit a rough patch, but I had hoped we could work it out next weekend when
我知道我们遇到了困难，但我曾希望下周末
we both had some time off.
我们都有空时能解决。
I think he found someone else.
我觉得他找了别人。
I had been getting suspicious because he had been spending a lot of time with a co-worker.
我一直怀疑，因为他花了很多时间和一个同事在一起。
Whatever.
随便吧。
He's a jerk.
他是个混蛋。
Forget about him.
忘了他吧。
There are many more fish in the sea.
天涯何处无芳草。
Talk about being cliche, Maggie.
你还说我老套呢，Maggie。
But you're right.
但你说得对。
There's no use for me to sulk around.
我闷闷不乐也没用。
Let's go out tonight.
我们今晚出去吧。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So obviously this girl, Lydia, is very torn.
很明显，这个女孩Lydia非常伤心。
She's very sad because her boyfriend broke up with her.
她很难过，因为男朋友和她分手了。
That's right.
没错。
She's crying the whole time this dialogue was going on.
整个对话过程中她一直在哭。
That's right.
没错。
But she did mention, her and her friend mentioned some interesting things.
但她和她的朋友提到了一些有趣的事情。
Why don't we take a look at some of the words they used on Language Takeaway.
我们来看看他们在“语言要点”中用到的一些词吧。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
So first of all, her friend says, hey, do you want to go out tonight?
首先，她的朋友说，嘿，今晚想出去吗？
And what does Lydia say?
Lydia怎么回答的？
She says, no, I think I'll pass.
她说，不，我想我就不去了。
All right.
好的。
So she says, I think I'll pass.
所以她说，我想我就不去了。
I will pass.
我就不去了。
So what does this verb mean, to pass?
那么这个动词“pass”是什么意思？
So that means she is politely rejecting the offer or the invitation.
意思是她礼貌地拒绝了提议或邀请。
So no thanks.
所以就是不了，谢谢。
No thanks.
不了，谢谢。
That's basically what it means.
基本上就是这个意思。
I won't go.
我不去。
So, hey, Marco, you want to go see a movie in a couple hours?
所以，嘿，Marco，你几个小时后想去看电影吗？
No, I think I'll pass.
不，我想我就不去了。
I got homework to do.
我有作业要做。
All right.
好的。
So Marco will not come.
所以Marco不会来。
That means to decline an invitation.
意思是拒绝邀请。
That's right.
没错。
So that's what it means to pass.
这就是“pass”的意思。
Now, as they continue to talk, they mention some of the problems with their boyfriend,
现在，他们继续聊，提到了和男朋友的一些问题，
but Maggie said, ugh, that's so cliche.
但Maggie说，呃，这太老套了。
So the boyfriend said something and Maggie thinks that what he said was very, very cliche.
所以男朋友说了些话，Maggie觉得他说得非常老套。
So what is something that is cliche?
那么什么是老套的东西？
Cliche means something that is said or done very often.
老套指的是经常说或做的事情。
It's almost like we would expect it.
几乎是我们预料之中的。
So like, for example, what's a cliche phrase or a cliche action?
比如，什么是老套的短语或行为？
Well, in the dialogue, they were talking about ways of breaking up with people.
在对话中，他们谈论的是分手的方式。
So for example, it's not you, it's me.
比如，不是你的问题，是我的问题。
Let's break up.
我们分手吧。
So that's a cliche because it's a sentence, it's a phrase everyone always says.
这很老套，因为这是一个句子，是每个人都会说的短语。
It's not very, maybe not very honest.
可能不太诚实。
Or like a movie cliche would be, you know, a couple, they're getting married, but their
或者像电影里的老套情节，比如一对情侣要结婚了，但
parents, the parents of the bride, they're divorced.
新娘的父母离婚了。
They hate each other.
他们互相讨厌。
But then at the wedding, they get back together.
但在婚礼上，他们又复合了。
They're going to get married again.
他们又要结婚了。
That's a cliche story.
那是个老套的故事。
That's right.
没错。
Because you've heard it before.
因为你以前听过。
Right.
对。
All the time.
总是这样。
It's very common.
这很常见。
So something that's very common, something that you would expect, that's almost, that's
所以，非常常见、你能预料到的事情，几乎就是——
a cliche.
老套。
And a cliche, calling something a cliche is not a good thing.
而说某件事老套，并不是什么好事。
It's usually a bad thing.
通常是个坏事。
That's right.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
So Maggie goes on to say that, you know, this guy, Mark, her ex-boyfriend, he's not really
所以玛吉接着说，你知道，这个家伙，马克，她的前男友，他其实——
worth it.
不值得。
But she says, you deserve so much better.
但她说，你值得更好的。
Okay.
好的。
So to deserve is a verb and it means that you should receive something or you should
所以“deserve”是一个动词，意思是你应该得到某物或——
expect something.
期待某物。
So almost like, you know, in this case, you deserve better.
所以差不多就像，你知道，在这种情况下，你值得更好的。
You have earned something better.
你赢得了更好的东西。
You're a good person.
你是个好人。
You should receive a, you know, you should have a good boyfriend.
你应该得到一个，你知道，你应该有一个好男朋友。
That's right.
没错。
So when, when she says you deserve so much better, she's talking about deserving a better
所以当她说到“你值得更好的”时，她指的是值得一个更好的——
guy, a better man.
男人，一个更好的男人。
Or for example, so Marco, you work so hard at school.
或者举个例子，马可，你在学校那么努力。
You're always doing your homework.
你总是做作业。
You really deserve good grades.
你真的值得好成绩。
It means you should receive good grades.
意思是你应该得到好成绩。
Very good.
非常好。
Now, when Lydia said, yeah, you know what?
现在，当莉迪亚说，是啊，你知道吗？
I just thought we were having some problems and we had hit a rough patch.
我只是觉得我们之间有些问题，我们遇到了困难时期。
So she's talking about a rough patch.
所以她提到了“rough patch”。
What is that?
那是什么？
A rough patch is actually something we talk about a lot in spoken English.
“Rough patch”实际上是我们口语中经常谈论的东西。
It's a way to describe a period of time, so maybe a week or a month when things are difficult,
它是一种描述一段时期的方式，可能是一周或一个月，当事情困难的时候，
you know, when maybe you argue with your boyfriend or girlfriend or when you're sad a lot or
你知道，也许你和男朋友或女朋友吵架，或者你经常伤心，或者——
when you're confused.
你感到困惑。
And so a period of time when you're angry or sad with your boyfriend or girlfriend,
所以一段你和男朋友或女朋友生气或伤心的时期，
that's a rough patch.
那就是“rough patch”。
So maybe we can apply a rough patch to another situation like at work.
所以我们也许可以把“rough patch”应用到其他情况，比如工作中。
Maybe you're going through a rough patch at work.
也许你正在经历工作中的困难时期。
That means I'm always busy.
那意味着我总是很忙。
I'm always tired.
我总是很累。
I don't feel happy with my job.
我对工作不满意。
I'm going through a rough patch.
我正在经历困难时期。
So it's usually a temporary period of time where things are going bad.
所以这通常是一段暂时的、事情不顺利的时期。
It could be a week.
可能是一周。
It could be a month.
可能是一个月。
It could be a year.
可能是一年。
But it's a fixed amount of time.
但这是一段固定的时间。
It's not forever.
不是永远。
It's just a period.
只是一段时期。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And Lydia went on to say that, you know, she thought that maybe he was going out with someone
莉迪亚接着说，你知道，她以为他可能和别人约会，
else and she was suspicious because he was spending a lot of time with some other girl.
她很怀疑，因为他花了很多时间和另一个女孩在一起。
Okay, so to be suspicious is to think that something is happening, but you don't know.
好的，所以“suspicious”是认为某事正在发生，但你不知道。
So for example, Marco, I think you've been taking the milk from the kitchen.
比如，马可，我觉得你一直在从厨房拿牛奶。
You are always drinking coffee and you always take milk in your coffee and there's no more
你总是喝咖啡，而且你总是在咖啡里加牛奶，现在没有——
milk.
牛奶了。
So I think it was you.
所以我觉得是你。
I'm being suspicious.
我表示怀疑。
I'm thinking that maybe you did something bad or wrong.
我在想也许你做了什么坏事或错事。
But I'm guilty.
但我有罪。
So maybe you're suspicious that someone is stealing the milk or maybe you suspect or
所以也许你怀疑有人在偷牛奶，或者你怀疑——
you're suspicious that your next door neighbor is maybe a car thief.
你怀疑你的邻居可能是个偷车贼。
Right.
对。
So you're very suspicious.
所以你非常怀疑。
That means you're always thinking that this person or someone else is doing something
那意味着你总是认为这个人或其他人正在做坏事——
bad.
坏事。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, so a lot of words there talking about relationships, talking about cliches.
好的，所以这里有很多关于关系、关于老套的词语。
Why don't we go back?
我们为什么不回去呢？
Let's listen to the dialogue again and we'll be back in a bit with Fluency Builder.
让我们再听一遍对话，稍后我们会回来进行流利度训练。
Hello?
喂？
Hey, do you want to go out tonight?
嘿，你今晚想出去吗？
No, I think I'll pass.
不，我想我就不去了。
Mark broke up with me.
马克和我分手了。
I feel awful.
我感觉糟透了。
What?
什么？
What happened?
发生什么事了？
Just last week you were talking about going on vacation together.
就在上周你还在说一起去度假的事。
I don't know what I did wrong.
我不知道我做错了什么。
He said he needed some space to figure things out.
他说他需要一些空间来理清事情。
He said I didn't do anything wrong, that I'm a great person, just not the one for him.
他说我没做错任何事，我是个很好的人，只是不是他的那个人。
That's so cliche.
这也太老套了。
Mark's not worth your time, Lydia.
马克不值得你浪费时间，莉迪亚。
You deserve so much better.
你值得更好的。
I know we had hit a rough patch, but I had hoped we could work it out next weekend when
我知道我们遇到了困难，但我本来希望下周末我们都有空的时候能解决。
we both had some time off.
我们都有空的时候。
I think he found someone else.
我觉得他找到别人了。
I had been getting suspicious because he had been spending a lot of time with a co-worker.
我一直有点怀疑，因为他最近和同事待在一起的时间很多。
Whatever.
随便吧。
He's a jerk.
他是个混蛋。
Forget about him.
忘了他吧。
There are many more fish in the sea.
天涯何处无芳草。
Talk about being cliche, Maggie.
玛吉，你这话才叫老套呢。
But you're right.
但你说得对。
There's no use for me to sulk around.
我在这儿闷闷不乐也没用。
Let's go out tonight.
我们今晚出去吧。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
Now let's take a look at some of those phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在让我们看看“流利度构建器”中的一些短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
All right, so Marco, these are cliche phrases that we hear in English when people are breaking
好的，马可，这些是英语中人们在分手时听到的老套说法。
up.
分手时的一些说法。
There's some breaking up phrases, but there's also phrases that you might hear from your
但也有一些是你分手后朋友可能会对你说的话。
friend after you have a breakup.
The first phrase we're going to look at, I think, is to need space.
我们要看的第一个短语，我想是“需要空间”。
He said he needed some space.
他说他需要一些空间。
That's a cliche phrase, as we said, but it means that maybe her ex-boyfriend or Mark
就像我们说的，这是个老套的说法，但意思是她的前男友或马克需要更多空间，需要更多时间独处或做自己的事。
needs more space, needs more time to be on his own or needs more time to do his own things.
需要更多时间独处或做自己的事。
That's right.
没错。
When you're in a relationship, you have a boyfriend or a girlfriend, you're always together.
当你谈恋爱时，有男朋友或女朋友，你们总在一起。
I need some space means I want to be alone.
“我需要一些空间”意思是我想一个人待着。
I don't want to be with my boyfriend or girlfriend.
我不想和男朋友或女朋友在一起。
Sometimes this is just a small period.
有时这只是短暂的一段时间。
Sometimes it's forever.
有时是永远。
It depends.
看情况。
That's right.
没错。
When somebody says that they need space, it means they need a little bit of more time
当有人说他们需要空间时，意思是他们需要多一点时间独处或一个人待着，就像你说的。
to be on their own or to be alone, as you said.
就像你说的。
He had also given her another cliche phrase.
他还给了她另一个老套的说法。
Mark said that she is not the one for him.
马克说她不是他的那个人。
Okay, so the emphasis here is the one.
好的，所以重点在“那个人”上。
The one.
那个人。
She's not the one for him.
她不是他的那个人。
In English, we often talk about the one.
在英语中，我们经常谈论“那个人”。
This means the person that you will marry, the love of your life.
意思是你将结婚的人，你一生的挚爱。
Your significant other, your other half.
你的另一半，你的伴侣。
That's right.
没错。
You hope that you will marry the one.
你希望你会和“那个人”结婚。
Her boyfriend realized.
她的男朋友意识到了。
He said, listen, I like you, but you're not the one.
他说，听着，我喜欢你，但你不是那个人。
You're not the person that I will marry.
你不是我会结婚的人。
This is a phrase you often hear in breakups.
这是你在分手时经常听到的短语。
If you're single, maybe you don't have a boyfriend or you're not married, you might say that
如果你单身，也许你没有男朋友或没结婚，你可能会说你还没找到“那个人”。
you haven't found the one.
或者，是的，你有很多不同的男朋友，但你还是没找到“那个人”。
Or yeah, you have a lot of different boyfriends, but you still haven't found the one.
意思是你将结婚的人。
That means the one you will marry.
没错。
That's right.
Very good.
很好。
And now towards the end of the dialogue, Maggie also gives her some advice and said, you know
现在在对话的结尾，玛吉也给了她一些建议，说，你知道吗？
what?
你知道吗？
Forget about him.
忘了他吧。
There are many more fish in the sea.
天涯何处无芳草。
Okay, so this is a phrase that we often say when we're trying to make somebody feel better.
好的，所以这是我们试图让人感觉好点时经常说的短语。
So the person is sad and we want to make them happy.
所以那个人很伤心，我们想让他们开心。
And so there are many more fish in the sea means that there are other men in the world.
“天涯何处无芳草”意思是世界上还有其他男人。
Okay, you're sad.
好的，你很难过。
You broke up.
你分手了。
I understand.
我理解。
But there are so many other men you could date.
但还有很多其他男人你可以约会。
So she's trying to say, hey, listen, look at this world.
所以她试图说，嘿，听着，看看这个世界。
There's so many different options.
有这么多不同的选择。
That's right.
没错。
So it's the similarity of how in the sea you have so many fish, in the world you have so
所以这就像海里有很多鱼，世界上有很多男人，所以别担心。
many men, so don't worry about it.
所以别担心。
And you can say this about women too.
你也可以用这个说法来形容女人。
So for example, if I'm talking to my male friend or my brother and my brother just broke
所以举个例子，如果我在跟我的男性朋友或兄弟说话，而他刚和女朋友分手，
up with his girlfriend, I can say, hey, listen, there are many more fish in the sea, many
我可以说，嘿，听着，天涯何处无芳草，还有很多
other women.
其他女人。
So don't worry about it.
所以别担心了。
Don't worry about it.
别担心了。
You'll be okay.
你会没事的。
And Lydia says, you know what?
然后莉迪亚说，你知道吗？
I think you're right.
我觉得你说得对。
And there's really no use for me to sulk around.
而且我确实没必要闷闷不乐。
So what does she mean to sulk around?
那么她说的“闷闷不乐”是什么意思？
To sulk.
闷闷不乐。
Now this is something that is very visual for me.
这个对我来说画面感很强。
I see somebody sulking.
我看到有人在生闷气。
Their head is low.
他们低着头。
They're sad.
他们很伤心。
Someone who is sulking often wears their sweatpants or their pajamas.
生闷气的人通常穿着运动裤或睡衣。
They don't make themselves look good.
他们不打扮自己。
To sulk around means to be in your house, to be sad, to watch TV and eat ice cream.
闷闷不乐的意思就是待在家里，伤心，看电视，吃冰淇淋。
So stop sulking.
所以别生闷气了。
Don't look sad.
别一副伤心的样子。
Be happy.
开心点。
To sulk is to act sad and to be very down.
生闷气就是表现得悲伤，情绪非常低落。
So it's kind of like you're very, it's kind of a combination of being lazy and also sad
所以这有点像你非常，它有点像懒惰和悲伤的结合，
at the same time because something bad happened to you.
同时因为发生了不好的事情。
Exactly.
没错。
And so we often say that in English, teenagers like to sulk.
在英语中，我们常说青少年喜欢生闷气。
You know, oh, I'm so angry at my parents.
你知道，哦，我对我父母很生气。
And your parents will say, hey, stop sulking.
然后你父母会说，嘿，别生闷气了。
Go study.
去学习。
That's right.
说得对。
Very good.
很好。
Okay.
好的。
So a lot of great phrases here.
这里有很多很棒的短语。
I think we can go back.
我觉得我们可以回顾一下。
Let's watch the dialogue one last time.
让我们最后看一遍对话。
Hello?
喂？
Hey, do you want to go out tonight?
嘿，今晚想出去吗？
No, I think I'll pass.
不，我想我就不去了。
Mark broke up with me.
马克和我分手了。
I feel awful.
我感觉糟透了。
What?
什么？
What happened?
发生什么事了？
Just last week you were talking about going on vacation together.
就在上周你还在说一起去度假的事。
I don't know what I did wrong.
我不知道自己做错了什么。
He said he needed some space to figure things out.
他说他需要一些空间来理清事情。
He said I didn't do anything wrong, that I'm a great person, just not the one for him.
他说我没做错什么，我是个很好的人，只是不适合他。
That's so cliche.
这也太老套了吧。
Mark's not worth your time, Lydia.
马克不值得你浪费时间，莉迪亚。
You deserve so much better.
你值得更好的人。
I know we had hit a rough patch, but I had hoped we could work it out next weekend when
我知道我们之前遇到了困难，但我本来希望下周末我们能解决这个问题，那时
we both had some time off.
我们都有空。
I think he found someone else.
我觉得他找到别人了。
I had been getting suspicious because he had been spending a lot of time with a co-worker.
我早就起疑心了，因为他最近和同事待在一起的时间很多。
Whatever.
随便吧。
He's a jerk.
他就是个混蛋。
Forget about him.
忘了他吧。
There are many more fish in the sea.
天涯何处无芳草。
Talk about being cliche, Maggie.
玛吉，你这说法也太老套了。
But you're right.
但你说得对。
There's no use for me to sulk around.
我在这儿闷闷不乐也没用。
Let's go out tonight.
今晚我们出去吧。
All right.
好的。
So talking about breakups, these cliche lines, and Maggie's obviously upset.
所以说到分手，这些老套的台词，玛吉显然很难过。
What other cliche lines or breakup phrases have you heard apart from, it's not you, it's
除了“不是你的问题，是我的问题”和“你不是那个对的人”之外，你还听过哪些老套的分手台词？
me, you're just not the one.
我，你不是那个对的人。
I need some space.
我需要一些空间。
I think of you more like a friend.
我更把你当朋友。
There's a boyfriend or girlfriend, but then there's a friend.
有男朋友或女朋友，但还有朋友。
So listen, I like you, but I think of you more like a friend.
所以听着，我喜欢你，但我更把你当朋友。
I think that's a typical one.
我觉得这是个典型的老套说法。
Especially if you're asking someone out on a date, they might say that, oh, I really
特别是如果你约某人出去，他们可能会说，哦，我真的
like you, but I see you more as a friend than anything else.
喜欢你，但我更把你当朋友而不是别的。
So there's another one that's very popular.
所以还有一个很流行的说法。
Sometimes you hear people say, I'm just not ready for a relationship.
有时你会听到人们说，我只是还没准备好谈恋爱。
And that's also a cliche line.
这也是个老套的台词。
Or I'm not ready to commit.
或者我还没准备好承诺。
I'm not ready to commit.
我还没准备好承诺。
And it's interesting because I think breaking up is one of the hardest things that people
有趣的是，我觉得分手是人们最难做到的事情之一
can do.
能做到的事。
And I think maybe this is why you just use one of these phrases that are so popular and
我想也许这就是为什么人们会用这些流行的老套台词之一。
common because I guess it's kind of a good way to explain in very soft terms what you
常见，因为我觉得这是一种用非常委婉的方式表达你想说的话，以及和某人分手的好方法。
want to say and to break up with someone.
没错。
That's right.
And I think that sometimes people are afraid to make the other person sad.
我觉得有时候人们害怕让对方伤心。
And so they say these things that are very general, like it's not you, it's me.
所以他们会说一些很笼统的话，比如“不是你的问题，是我的问题”。
But sometimes this makes the other person even more sad because they don't understand
但有时候这会让对方更难过，因为他们不明白
why that they're breaking up.
为什么要分手。
What about breaking up over the telephone or breaking up with a letter?
那通过电话分手或者写信分手呢？
Generally, at least in America, we say that breaking up over email or letter or phone
一般来说，至少在美国，我们认为通过电子邮件、信件或电话分手
is not a good way to end a relationship.
不是结束一段关系的好方式。
It's very cold.
这太冷漠了。
So the other person would be very angry if that happened.
所以如果那样做，对方会很生气。
That's right.
没错。
You just want to see the person and say, listen, let's have a conversation.
你只想见到那个人，然后说，听着，我们谈谈吧。
Let's talk about this face to face.
我们面对面谈谈这件事。
Okay.
好的。
So this is actually very interesting because as we say, maybe in other countries or in
所以这其实很有趣，因为就像我们说的，也许在其他国家或
other cultures, it's not really a negative thing to break up over the phone or maybe
其他文化中，通过电话分手或者
send an email saying, you know what, I don't want to see you anymore.
发封邮件说“你知道吗，我不想再见到你了”并不完全是坏事。
Right.
对。
So I'd be very curious to hear about you guys and your cultures and what happens when people
所以我很好奇你们和你们的文化，以及你们那里的人
break up where you live.
分手时会发生什么。
So let us know.
所以告诉我们吧。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是EnglishPod.com。
We hope to see you there.
希望在那里见到你们。
And of course, we hope that you haven't had any very bad breakup experiences.
当然，我们希望你们没有经历过任何非常糟糕的分手经历。
But if you're comfortable sharing, we'd like to hear about your culture and your background.
但如果你们愿意分享，我们想听听你们的文化和背景。
All right.
好了。
So we'll see you guys there.
那我们到时候见。
Bye.
再见。